Andrey Omelyanuk

Tech Lead / Senior Full Stack Developer (Python/TypeScript)

• Exp.: over 15 years (sinse Oct 2008)

• Legal name: Andrei Amelyaniuk

• Location: Belarus, Brest or Armenia, Yerevan

Russian: Native

• English: Intermediate

• Email: omelyanukandrey@gmail.com

• GitHub: https://github.com/Andrey-Omelyanuk

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/andrey-omelyanuk-36904154/

• UpWork: https://www.upwork.com/o/profiles/users/_~01b1cfb09d499e00cb/

Python, Django, Django REST Framework, FastAPI, SQLAlchemy, Celery, SQL, PostgreSQL, Ansible, Docker, JavaScript, TypeScript, Vue, React, Angular, RxJs, MobX

About

I am an experienced senior software developer passionate about automating the world. I enjoy working on projects that allow people to be more productive. I have experience in leading engineering teams as well as developing software independently as an individual contributor.

Experience

ITSOFT | Commit Offshore

https://www.itsoft.co.il/

Senior Python Engineer

March 2024 - May 2024 (3 months)

Python, Django, Django REST framework, AWS

Team

1-2 developers

https://md2pdf.netlify.app 1/6

Intelas

https://intelas.com/

It's SaaS that collects and standardizes property-level data for real estate asset managers and accountants.

I was the first developer hired at the startup. When I left Intelas, the company had 11 developers (including me). The company canceled the remote work format and required all developers to relocate to Lisbon, Portugal. I was in Portugal for 5 months, but I was very disappointed (very expensive life, high taxes, lots of crime) and decided to leave Portugal. Unfortunately this also meant that I had to leave the startup. I am very proud to have built this startup from scratch and I am grateful to everyone I worked with there. It was one of the best experiences of my career. You can contact Leonid to get personal feedback about me.

Tech Lead

March 2022 - Nov 2023 (1.8 years)

Python, Django, DRF, SQL, PostgreSQL, Docker, AWS, Typescript, React, MobX, AgGrid, Senty

Team

11 developers

Responsibilities and Achievements

- led the team
- interviewed software developers
- teached the team, for example how to build UI with MobX
- built architecture of the project
- worked on workflow for my team
- discussed business needs with owners
- distributed responsibilities between developers
- did all things till delegate it to another developer

Virtual Clarity

https://www.virtualclarity.com/

It was SaaS. A lot of companies have old apps and servers. Our goal was help them to migrate to modern solution like a cloud or new servers with fresh version OS. We collected information about the client's infrastructure and provided options for its modernization and calculated the costs for this. We built forecast of future expenses of maintain and compared with current expenses.

https://md2pdf.netlify.app 2/6

Tech Lead / Senior Full Stack Developer

June 2019 – Dec 2021 (2.5 years)

```
Jun 2021 - Dec 2021 (0.5 years) Tech Lead Frontend Developer
Jun 2019 - Jun 2021 ( 2 years) Senior Full Stack Developer
```

Python, Django, SqlAlchemy, MSSQL, AWS, Docker, Typescript, Angular, RxJs, MobX, AgGrid

Team

5-7 developers

Responsibilities and Achievements

- we had separate DB based on MSSQL which was managed and maintained from another team, therefor I used SQLAlchemy for glue Django with the DB, Django ORM don't support MSSQL.
 Before I joined they used own custom ORM to do it, but it was buggy and featureless.
- created and optimized complex SQL queries
- when we started build new UI I had lead frontend. It was based on Angular (we use Django templates before)

Zig

https://zigtheapp.xyz

Zig is startup, its mix of task management and freelance platform. The project was 80% completed before I left. The site is not available now but the design is still available here

Team Lead / Senior Full Stack Developer

Sep 2015 - May 2019 (3.7 years)

```
Jun 2016 - May 2019 (2.8 years) Team Lead Full Stack Developer
Sep 2015 - Jun 2016 (0.9 years) Senior Full Stack Developer
```

Python, Django, Django REST Framework, Celery, PostgreSQL, HTML, Pug, CSS, Stylus, JavaScript, TypeScript, Webpack, Angular, Vue.js, JSData, RxJS, Cordova, Ansible

Team

```
3-5 developers, 1 web-designer
```

https://md2pdf.netlify.app 3/6

Responsibilities and Achievements

- led the team and the project
- interviewed software developers
- developed mobile (Android and iOS) version using Cordova
- used PubNub for sending async messages to clients
- used Sentry to gather error logs from back-end and front-end
- built architecture of the application
- did everything that the project required except web design and things that I could delegate to other developers (usually I delegated UI tasks).

More details

I led the project.

The project was started with Angular 1 and with no data layer.

When I joined, I split the project into two parts (back and front).

This has facilitated the work of front-end developers (they know nothing about back-end, they Also, we started to use js-data https://www.js-data.io/v2.9/docs/home for the data layer, Pug instead of pure HTML and Stylus instead of pure CSS.

Later I tried to use TypeScript and I liked it and we migrated to TypeScript. It was very easy After 2 year, I was disappointed with Angular 1 (terrible performance and I didn't believe to and we migrated to Vue.js (performance much better now! some tests showed boost up to x15). After Vue migration, I integrated MobX into js-data for reactivity.

On the backend, I used Django + Django Rest Framework.

These tools helped me to build REST API very quickly and effectively.

I integrated the PubNub service for async messages from the back-end to the front-end(web and and I used it for new messages in a chat and user notifications.

For long tasks that should be run in the background, I used Celery with RabbitMQ broker.

I had no performance issues on the backend, all queries to DB were optimized by me,

all tables used correct indexes. Actually, it was not a big win because I had not a lot of dat production DB had a ~400MB size and grew not too fast (~30MB per month).

I integrated Sentry to gather errors from users.

I planned to split the monolith back-end into microservices (auth and message microservices) b





Nord-Soft

http://nord-soft.com/

Senior Full Stack Developer

Jan 2013 - May 2015 (2.4 years)

Python, Django, Django REST Framework, Celery, PostgreSQL, Redis, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, jQuery, Angular, Git, Mercurial, Bootstrap

https://md2pdf.netlify.app 4/6

Team

1-7 developers

Responsibilities and Achievements

- developed a lot of small/middle web projects
- leading projects from scratch to final
- development software architecture
- development front-end and back-end
- deploying projects on servers

Interesting tasks that I remember

• Video montage.

A web application that makes a video from pictures and soundtracks. I used Celery to run a background job and FFmpeg for making a video.

Optimized DB query.

It was a company that repairs airplanes. They had a web application for counting repairs. It was a very unusual DB schema, they used PostgreSQL table inheritance and it made a problem for performance. I made the query faster ~20% using indexes but it still was not acceptable. The last option was to remove table inheritance and required a lot of time to refactor. The customer did not agree to make the refactoring and bought a more powerful server.

System Technologies

https://www.st.by

Junior/Middle Software Developer

```
Oct 2008 - Dec 2012 (4.2 years)
```

```
Jan 2010 - Dec 2012 ( 3 years) Middle Software Developer Oct 2008 - Dec 2010 (1.2 years) Junior Software Developer
```

C++, MFC, T-SQL (Sybase)

Team

```
6-10 developers, 6 testers, 3 business analytics.
```

https://md2pdf.netlify.app 5/6

Responsibilities and Achievements

- developed reports for business (created SQL procedures and UI using C++)
- developed templates for new contracts and other business documents
- analyzed and optimized many heavy SQL queries (Production DB size is ~80TB)
- analyzed and fixed many deadlocks
- developed UI for new features using C++
- developed and maintained an internal tool for version control for Sybase using C++

Education

Brest State Technical University

http://en.bstu.by/

Sep 2003 – Jul 2008 (5 years)

Bachelor's degree, Computer science

https://md2pdf.netlify.app 6/6